Talents have been hated for thousands of years since ancient times,
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Forty-three]
[第四十三集]
So I hope
所以我希望
we the Peking University Marxist Theory Research Society
我们北京大学马克思学说研究会
and the soon-to-be-established
和即将成立的
Beijing branch of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党北京支部的同志们
must actively participate in these two great debates.
一定要积极地参加这两个大论战
Make our stance clear.
旗帜鲜明地表明我们的态度
"New Youth"
《新青年》
and the upcoming "Communist Party" magazine
和即将创刊的 《共产党》 杂志
are our position.
就是我们的阵地
Hurrah!
好
Brother Jiemin, you're going abroad for a study tour.
子民兄 你此次出国考察
If you hadn't left from Shanghai,
若不是从上海出发
I will try my best to see you off in Beijing.
我也必定会想方设法去北京相送
At Peking University,
先生在北大
there are two initiatives can be credited to you.
有两项举措可谓功不可没
One, reform in education.
教育改革
It has changed the mindset and virtue
改变了一代学子们的
of a generation of scholars
观念和德行
and promoted the development of the New Culture Movement.
促进了新文化运动的发展
The second is compatibility and inclusiveness.
二是兼容并包
In Peking University, there are various doctrines
北大内有各种学说
that can be studied as one wishes,
随已所愿研究
so it is not enough to take into account the ruin and reputation,
是以毁誉不足计
but what is valuable to the trend
而趋向之所宝贵者
is also the spirit.
则精神也
I admire it.
佩服
Zhongfu, you flatter me.
仲甫 你过誉了
Brother Botang.
伯棠兄啊
I should really thank you for all these years.
这些年我真应该好好感谢你
Thank you, brother Botang.
感谢佰棠兄
All these years have given me so many ideas.
这些年给我出了那么多馒主意
Jiemin, you really have to thank me.
子民啊 你还真得感谢我
Your time at Peking University
你在北大的这段时光
will be unforgettable for the rest of your life.
必会让你终生难忘
Zhongfu.
仲甫啊
I hear there's another fight between you.
我听说你们内部又斗起来了
What are you crazy about Wu?
你这吴疯子又说什么疯话
Controversies on socialism.
社会主义论战
You criticized Zhang Dongsun.
你批判了张东荪
Controversies on anarchism.
无政府主义论战
You criticized Huang Lingshuang.
你批判了黄凌霜
When are you going to
你打算什么时候
criticize I Wu Zhihui and Chen Yannian?
批判我吴稚晖和陈延年哪
Let me tell you something.
我告诉你啊
I can save your face.
我可给你留着面子呢
You followed Russell, I didn't point it out.
你追随罗素 我没有点破
You encouraged Huang Lingshuang to quit the Communist Party.
你鼓动黄凌霜退出共产党
I'm not arguing with you either.
我也没有跟你计较
Because we're not
因为咱俩本来就不是
cars in the same lane,
一股道上的车
there is no need to quarrel.
犯不着吵架
But I have to warn you about one thing.
但是有一点我必须要警告你
Don't touch Yannian and Qiaonian again.
不许再打延年和乔年的主意
What kind of path they want to choose
他们要选择什么样的道
is their own choice.
是他们自己的选择
You have no right to interfere.
你没有权利横加干涉
I took an oath long ago.
我早就发过誓
I don't care about your family's mess.
再也不管你家的破事了
In a Shanghai we have a saying,
用一句上海话说
"I don't get along with you".
我和你不来电
Zhongfu, as a brother,
仲甫啊作为兄长
I have a few words of truth to tell you.
我有几句真心话想跟你说
People often say that different things do not work together.
人常说 道不同不相为谋
You and I have different ways,
你我之间 道虽不同
but we can work together.
亦可为谋
The New Culture Movement is you, Shouchang, Shizhi,
新文化运动是你和守常 适之
and Mr. Lu Xun.
还有鲁迅先生
You guys started this.
你们这几个人掀起来的
Now some differences are inevitable.
现在有些分歧 在所难免
But don't let this
但不要因为这个
and hurt your kindness to each other.
而伤了彼此的和气
Before I came here this time,
这次我来之前
I told Shizhi.
我告诉适之
He wants to come to Shanghai and have a good talk with you.
要他到上海来与你好好谈一谈
Sir, you are right.
先生瞩附得是
Recently, I have planned to
最近我已经打算
to invite Shouchang and Shizhi to Shanghai for a get-together.
请守常和适之来上海一聚了
Excellent.
太好了
Shouchang, Shizhi.
守常 适之
I will go to Guangzhou soon.
我很快就要去广州了
This time, my family moved south to Guangdong for schooling.
这次举家南迁去广东办教育
I'm afraid I'm going to live there for a while.
恐怕要在那儿住上一段时间了
What worries me is what to do with "New Youth".
我所担心的是 《新青年》 怎么办
It's everyone's child.
它是我们大家的孩子
What should it be a home for?
它应该是一个什么样的归宿
This needs to be decided by everyone.
这需要大家来定
For this reason, I have written to
为此 我已经分别致信
Deqian, Yucai, and others
德潜 豫才等人
to ask for their opinions.
征求他们的意见
I sincerely invite you both to come to Shanghai for a get-together
我诚邀请你们二位能来沪面谈
to discuss and solve this problem together.
共同商量并解决好这个问题
I warmly look forward to you.
热烈地盼望你们
It is almost as hard for friends to meet as for the morning and evening stars.
人生不相见 动如参与商
Shouchang, Shizhi.
守常 适之
Thank you for taking the time to gather in Shanghai.
要感谢你们拨来沪上一聚
It's a relief for me!
了却我一桩心事啊
Talents have been hated for thousands of years since ancient times,
自古人才千载限
and they are still willing to make Erguotou.
至今甘醴二锅头
This is what I said when I first met Shizhi.
这是我初识适之时说的
Shizhi, remember?
适之还记得吗
Of course I remember.
当然记得了
My first day in Beijing,
我来北京第一天
you and Mr. Cai invited me to dinner at the scholar's residence
你和蔡先生在学士居请我吃的饭
to drink Erguotou.
咱们喝的就二锅头
Why, where shall we drink today?
怎么 今天咱们在哪儿喝呢
In the countryside.
山野间
Let's drink and talk.
把酒畅谈来
Come, brother Zhongfu.
来仲甫兄
I'd like to congratulate you first
小弟我首先要恭祝你
on your honorable appointment as the Chairman of the Education Committee of the Guangdong Government.
荣任广东政府教育委员会委员长
This is a big position.
这可是一个不小的官啊
I decided to go to Guangzhou
我决定去广州
not to be an official.
不是为了做官
I want to do something for the backward education in China.
是想为中国落后的教育做点事情
Just like when we started "New Youth",
就像当初我们办 《新青年》
wasn't it also to enlighten people's minds
不也是为了启蒙人的思想
and improve their quality?
提高人的素质吗
You mentioned "New Youth".
你提到 《新青年》
I was just going to ask you,
我还正想问你
why has
为什么咱们
a very good "New Youth"
一个好端端的《新青年》
become a publication of the Party?
却成了一个党派的刊物
Is the current "New Youth"
现在的 《新青年》
still the academic journal of enlightenment?
还是当初思想启蒙的学术刊物吗
Now that we're here.
既然聊到这儿了
Then let's discuss this matter.
那我们就议议这件事情
Before,
之前呢
I wrote to my colleagues in Beijing for advice.
我给北京同人去信征求意见
They wrote that
他们来信说
all the opinions have been summarized to Shizhi.
意见都汇总到适之你这儿了
Then Shizhi, tell me first.
那适之 你就先说说吧
I am not satisfied with the present situation of "New Youth".
我对 《新青年》 的现状很不满意
Several schemes are put forward for you to choose from.
提出了几个方案供大家进行选择
All the opinions are summarized in Shouchang's place.
意见都汇总在了守常那儿
Shouchang, tell me first.
守常 你先说说呗
Alright.
好
Since brother Zhongfu is going to work in Guangdong,
鉴于仲甫兄要去广东任职
Shizhi proposed three schemes.
适之提出了三个方案
The first one is to run another publication in Beijing.
第一个 在北京另外办一个刊物
The second one is to move "New Youth" to Beijing.
第二个把《新青年》 迁到北京
but to make a declaration that it will not talk about politics.
但是要发表一个不谈政治的宣言
The third, suspension.
第三 停办
These three opinions
这三条意见
Everyone is unanimously opposed.
大家一致反对
Everyone finally agreed
大家最后同意
since Zhongfu has no time to take care of it,
既然仲甫无暇顾及
the editor of "New Youth",
《新青年》 的编辑
you can move "New Youth" to Beijing.
可以把《新青年》 迁至北京
But what to do after moving to Beijing,
但是迁到北京之后怎么
we are very divided and can not be unified
大家的分歧很大 无法统一
Later, most people agreed with
后来大多数人还是同意了
Mr. Lu Xun's suggestion.
鲁迅先生的建议
Leaving the decision on the "New Youth"
把《新青年》 的决定权
to Zhongfu.
交给仲甫
Because "New Youth",
因为  《新青年》
is Zhongfu's creation after all.
毕竟是仲甫办的
Shizhi, am I right to say that?
适之 我这么说没错吧
You're right.
没错
But I personally don't agree.
但是我个人并不同意
The opinion of this majority
这多数人的意见
I also want to ask Zhongfu.
我也想问仲甫
If you are in Guangdong,
你身在广东
how can "New Youth" succeed?
《新青年》 以后怎么力
Where will it settle down?
落户什么地方
Who will preside over the editing?
谁来主持编辑
"New Youth" will stay in Shanghai.
《新青年》 继续留在上海
Chen Wangdao will be the editor.
由陈望道来主持编辑
Agreed.
同意
I have no objection.
我不反对
But I am really disappointed.
但是我真的很失望
I am also very sad.
我也很伤心
Shizhi, today, we're drinking wine and talking in the countryside.
适之 今天我们山野间把酒畅谈
Speak up if you have anything to say.
有什么话你直言
I am sad for the split of "New Youth".
我为《新青年》 的分裂而伤心
I am sad for your stubbornness.
我为你们的固执而伤心
More sad for your future.
更为你们的前途而伤心
Are we friends?
我们是朋友吧
I can't convince you, let alone stop you.
我无法说服 更不能阻止你们
I'm out of words now.
我现在已经词穷了
I'm only disappointed and sad.
我只剩下失望和伤心
Shizhi.
适之
I invited you and Shouchang to Shanghai today.
我今天把你和守常请到上海来
For "New Youth",
既是为了 《新青年》
I also want us to exchange ideas together.
也是想我们能一起交流思想
It must be admitted,
必须要承认
after the baptism of the May Fourth Movement
经过五四运动的洗礼
we had great differences
我们对国家的政治态度
in our country's political position.
产生了重大的分歧
Shouchang and I have made it clear
我和守常已经明确无误地
to ultimately choose Marxism,
选择了马克思主义
and hope to go on
希望能够通过
the road of Russia's October Revolution
俄国十月革命的道路
to save China.
来拯救中国
And finally, build
最终建立一个
a socialist country where the people are the masters of the country.
由人民当家做主的社会主义国家
This is my common ideal and pursuit with Shouchang.
这是我和守常共同的理想和追求
Your common ideal and pursuit.
你们两个人共同的理想和追求
Everyone knows this.
大家都知道
I was in the Red Building of Peking University two days ago.
前两天我在北大红楼
I heard some classmates singing a ballad.
听到几个同学在传唱一首歌谣
Two giants of the Peking University Red Building.
北大红楼两巨人
Northern Li and Southern Chen are widely spread.
纷传北李与南陈
The lone pine stands alone like a rafter pen.
孤松独秀如橡笔
The sun, moon and stars shine in the past and present.
日月双星照古今
But this is their opinion.
但这是他们的看法
And I disagree with the beliefs
而我对你们两个人的信仰
of the two of you.
不敢苟同
You say socialism can save China.
你们说社会主义它能救中压
Why then does Germany, the birthplace of socialism,
那为什么社会主义的发源地德国
not engage in socialism?
不搞社会主义
How many years has it been since the Russian revolution?
俄国革命才多少年
What makes you conclude that it is suitable for China?
你们凭么断定它适合中国
My opinion is that
我的主张是
China must copy the American system.
我们中国必须照搬美国的制度
I studied in America for seven years.
我在美国学习了七年
I have seen it through my own long-term personal experience
我是通过我自身长期的切身感受
and reached my conclusion.
得到的结论
What about you? Where did your conclusion come from?
你们呢你们的结论从何而来
Shizhi.
适之啊
I used to cross the ocean with brother Zhongfu
以前我跟仲甫兄漂洋过海
to seek truth.
去寻求真理
After so many years of ups and downs,
经过了那么多年的风风雨雨
after numerous choices and explorations,
经过了无数次的选择和探索
now we have finally determined a direction.
我们现在终于确定了一个方向
Marxism is a scientific truth.
马克思主义是科学真理
The October Revolution is our example.
十月革命是我们的榜样
The Western democracy you worship
你崇拜的那个西方的民主
doesn't work in China.
在中国根本行不通
Socialism can save the labouring masses.
社会主义能够解救劳苦大众
For this beautiful ideal,
为了这个美好理想
I am willing to give my all.
我愿意献出我的一切
Shizhi, I believe
适之 我相信
the Communist Party of China we established today
我们今天成立的中国共产党
is not just my choice with Shouchang,
并不仅仅是我和守常的选择
it is also a historical choice.
也是历史的选择
I believe there will be more and more Chinese people
我相信一定会有越来越多的中国人
who will agree to join this choice.
赞同和加入这个选择
Okay. Okay.
好好
I'm a minority today.
今天我是少数派
I won't argue with you.
我不和你们论了
I thought since it was a choice.
窃以为既然是选择
Friends should allow people to have their own interests.
朋友之间就应当允许人各有志
A gentleman gets along with others, but not necessarily agrees with them.
君子和而不同嘛
The three of us are here today,
我们三个人行至今日
although the faith is different, the friendship is deep.
信仰虽异 友情笃深
Only in this regard,
仅就此点
is it more precious.
弥足珍贵
A good friendship is precious.
好好一个友情笃深 弥足珍贵
I agree.
我同意
Shizhi, Shouchang.
适之守常
The three of us should always be honest with each other.
我们三个人当永远坦诚相待
As for the choice of faith,
至于信仰的选择
lLet's leave it to history to judge.
熟是熟非 留给历史评判吧
We got drunk in countryside today.
我们今日这山野间一醉
Tomorrow will be separated by mountains.
明日别后已是山岳相隔
The world is boundless.
世事茫
Spring trees in Northern Wei,
渭北春天树
sunset clouds in Eastern Jiang River.
江东日暮云
When can we drink,
何时一樽酒
and discuss our poems again?
重与细论文
[Paris, France]
来法国这么久了
Haven't you had a jiaozi yet?
还没吃过一顿饺子呢吧
Let you taste my craft today.
今天让你们尝尝我的手艺
Okay.
好
I can finally eat jiaozi.
终于能吃上饺子了
Yannian.
延年
This is from Mr. Zhongfu.
这是仲甫先生寄来的
I was told to give it to you by hand.
再三瞩我一定要亲手交给你
This is the fourth batch.
这已经是第四批了
It seems that if I don't follow my father,
看来我要是不跟着我父亲走
it's impossible for him to give up.
他是不可能撒手的
I heard it from Mr. Zhongfu with my own ears.
我可是亲耳听仲甫先生说
Qiaonian, Yannian, if you don't believe in Marxism,
乔年延年要是不信马克思主义
he will not die in peace.
他死也不会膜冒
Then please go back and tell him.
那就请你回去转告他
Please rest assured.
请他放心
Our brothers' beliefs have changed.
我们哥俩的信仰已经改变了
Changed?
改变了
Yes, it has changed.
对 改变了
Great.
太好了
How did you turn around this corner?
这个弯儿你们是怎么转过来的
It's not easy.
太不容易了
I've been in France for more than a year.
来法国一年多了
I see with my own eyes,
亲眼所见
all the experiments failed.
所有的试验都失败了
Anarchism can't save the world.
无政府主义它就救不了这个世界
Our belief in it in the past
我们过去对它的信仰
can only be said to be built on quicksand.
只能说是建立在浮沙之上
Now I read these books
现在读了这些书
and ponder over and over.
反复地琢磨
Marxism is science.
马克思主义才是科学
We want to dedicate this passion
我们要把这一腔的热血
to this wonderful ideal society.
献给这个美好的理想社会
Yannian.
延年
Are you sure you want to break with anarchism?
你确定要和无政府主义决裂了吗
Definitely.
确定 决裂
Classmates.
同学们
Today, it's representatives of our work-study students in France,
今天是我们留法勤工俭学生的代表
the Montagnards and Crusoeites.
蒙达尼派和克鲁梭派
Sitting together for the second time
第二次坐到一起
to discuss joint operations.
共同商讨联合行动事宜
The first time was to discuss the issue
第一次是共同商讨
of boycotting the Beiyang government's borrowing from France
联合抵制北洋政府向法国借款
and the purchase of arms.
和购买军火的问题
Today is the day to discuss the boycott
今天是商讨抵制里昂中法大学
of Lyon Sino-French University's refusal to admit work-study students.
拒收勤工俭学生入学的问题
[Li Weihan]
这是一个事关我们每个同学
the fate and future of each of us students.
命运和前途的问题
Next,
下面
please Zhao Shiyan introduce the situation to everyone.
请赵世炎同学给大家介绍一下情况
Classmates
同学们
Most of us
我们绝大多数人
has been here in France for more than a year.
来法国已经一年多了
But so far,
可是到现在为止
except for a few government-funded students,
除了少数的官费生之外
almost none of us
我们几乎没有人
have been able to enter the school.
能够进入到学校学习
In January this year,
今年一月
the Chinese law education society
华法教育学会
announces decoupling from work-study students.
宣布与勤工俭学生脱钩
The French Embassy stopped paying
法国大使馆停止发放对
living expenses of work-study students.
勤工俭学生的生活维持费
Now,
现在
Wu Zhihui, President of the Lyon Sino-French University,
里昂中法大学校长吴稚晖
cited the excuse that hardworking students
以勤工学生程度太低
were too under-educated to pay their own way,
无法自费为借口
violating of previous commitments and agreements,
违反了之前的承诺和协定
and unwilling to accept students studying in France for admission.
不愿意接受留法勤工俭学生入学
This is the worst thing
这对于我们来说
that could happen to us.
无异于是雪上加霜
What little hope there was of going to school
仅存一点上学的希望
was shamelessly cut off.
也被无耻地断送了
Classmates.
同学们
We can't sit on our hands any longer.
我们不能再坐以待了
We must act decisively.
我们必须果断采取行动
Right! Something has to be done!
必须得采取行动
Qinsheng.
琴生
Is the news of Wu Zhihui's treachery accurate?
吴稚晖背信弃义的消息确切吗
Yannian students can prove my information.
延年同学可以证明我说的信息
Ladies and gentlemen.
诸位
This magazine published in Singapore
这本新加坡出版的杂志
published the general enrollment brochure of Lyon University.
刊登了里昂大学的招生简章
It clearly states
明确规定
that if it is not a government fee or a guarantee of payment,
若非官费或有支付款项的确实保证
it cannot be included.
不得收录
This letter from China says
这封国内来信说
Lyon University has started enrolling students in China,
里昂大学已经开始在国内招生
who are taking the entrance exam and paying the tuition in full.
考试录取 并缴足学费
According to this admissions brochure,
按照这封招生简章
none of us work-study students
我们勤工俭学生
will be admitted.
将无一人能被录取
Yannian.
延年同学
Didn't Wu Zhihui repeatedly claim
吴稚晖不是多次宣称
that he would give priority to the admission of two sons of Chen Duxiu
会优先录取陈独秀的两位公子
to the University of Lyon?
进入里昂大学学习的吗
Runhuan, please rest assured.
润寰请放心
Chen Yannian and Chen Qiaonian
陈延年和陈乔年
must advance and retreat together.
一定和大家共进退
If he Wu Zhihui reneges,
如果他吴稚晖背信弃义
we two brothers will fight him to the end.
我们兄弟俩一定和他斗争到底
I propose
我提议
that all the work-study students rush to Lyon
全体勤工俭学生赶赴里昂
to protest at the Sino-French University
进驻中法大学
We will not stop until we achieve our goal!
不达自的 誓不罢休
Everybody, don't get excited.
大家不要激动
Let's not get excited yet.
大家先不要激动
We should treat this question
这个问题
more rationally.
我们应该更理智地去对待
I suggest
我建议
we send student representatives
咱们先派出学生代表
to fight directly
去找吴稚晖
with Wu Zhihui.
直接斗争
Yes!
好
Justice for us students... Students are not guilty!
还我学生公理 学生无罪
Wu Zhihui broke his promise!
吴稚晖出尔反尔
Zhou Enlai.
周恩来
What are you doing here?
你们这是千什么
This is all ridiculous, you!
太不像话了你们
Isn't this a riot?
这不是聚众闹事吗
Zhou Enlai.
周恩来
Gather your classmates here.
你把同学们集中到这儿
What do you want to do?
是想干什么
Do you want to force the palace?
难道想逼宫吗
Mr. Wu broke his promise,
吴先生出尔反尔
refusing to accept work-study students.
拒绝接受勤工俭学生入学
At the same time, you collaborated with Chen Lu and the French authorities
同时你勾结陈篆 法国当局
to persecute and unjustifiably expel
迫害并无理驱逐
work-study students from school.
勤工俭学学生入学
The fact is
事实证明
you are the culprit.
你是肇事的元区
You bunch of babies.
你们这些娃娃
How can you talk nonsense?
怎么能信口开河呢
I, Wu Zhihui, can't love you all enough
我吴稚晖爱你们都爱不过来
How can I lie to you?
我怎么舍得骗你们呢
We have ample evidence
我们有充分的证据
to prove that you are in cahoots with Chen Lu and others
证明你与陈篆等人狼驹为好
to deprive us of our right to enroll in school
用干分卑部的手段
by using the tactics of a subordinate department.
剥夺了我们入学的权利
You can't deny the evidence.
这些证据你是抵赖不掉的
Absolutely ridiculous!
荒唐透顶
How dare you slander me, Wu Zhihui?
你们竞敢迅麗我昊稚晖
For such slanderous words.
你们竟敢诬蔑我昊稚晖
Absolutely unacceptable!
断然不能接受
Yannian. Qiaonian.
延年 乔年
I treat you as my own.
我视你们如己出
You can prove that I'm clean.
你们可以证明我的清自
We can prove it.
会证明的
Yannian.
延年
Didn't you say you wanted to talk to Mr Wu?.
你不是说想要找吴先生谈谈吗
Now is the right time.
现在正是时候
Yannian.
延年
It's time to end it.
该做个了断了
Good.
好
Mr. Wu.
吴先生
I am waiting for you at the door with hundreds of work-study students.
我和几百名勤工俭学生在门口等你
Today,
今天
you must give us a definite answer.
你务必要给我们一个明确的答复
Excuse me for a moment.
你们先回避一下
You two come upstairs with me.
你们俩跟我上楼
Let's talk here.
就在这儿谈
I say.
我说
You two silly children.
你们两个傻孩子
How can you hang out with such people?
你们怎么能跟这种人混到一起呢
Mr. Wu Zhihui.
吴稚晖先生
We are here to break with you.
我们是来和你决裂的
You cheated us,
您欺骗了我们
cheated countless students who followed you
欺骗了无数跟着你
all the way to France for work-study.
不远万里来到法国勤工俭学的学生
I have my own difficulties.
我有我的苦衷
Yannian, you should know.
延年 你应该懂得
The Lyon Sino-French University is not a shelter.
里晶中法大学不是栖流所
It's not the world's greatest shelter.
更不是大庇天下寒士的广厦万间
But,
不过
I promise you both.
我向你们俩保证
I will keep my promise to you.
我对你们的承诺一定兑现
You should also understand us.
您也应该懂得我个
We will not give up our belief in being human.
我们不会放弃自已做人的信仰
But we can tell you,
但是 我们可以告诉您
We have abandoned the faith in anarchism
我们已经放弃了您教给我们的
that you taught us.
对无政府主义的信仰
So what do you believe in now?
那你们现在信仰什么
We believe in the beautiful ideal of socialism.
我们信仰社会主义的美好理想
You are confused!
糊涂
Mr. Wu Zhihui.
吴稚晖先生
We will walk the road under our feet.
我们脚下的路我们自己会走
I won't bother you.
就不劳您操心了
We await your reply.
我们等您的答复
Otherwise,
否则
we will never retreat.
我们决不后退
Mr. Wu.
吴先生
This is my translation of the "Internationale".
这是我翻译的 《国际歌》 副歌
Do you have time to have a look?
你有时间看一下
Yannian! Qiaonian!
延年 军乔年
You'll be sorry.
你们会后悔的
Forever doomed.
万劫不复
Marin
马林
Hello.
您好
Sit, sit.
坐坐坐
Thank you for waiting.
让二位久等了
Thank you.
谢谢
Gentlemen.
二位代表
Let me show you something.
给你们看样东西
This is a letter from Comrade Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao.
这个是陈独秀和李大钊同志的来信
In their letter,
他们在信中表示同意
they agreed to hold the first national congress
尽快在上海召开
of the Communist Party of China as soon as possible.
中国共产党第一次的全国代表大会
All branches are required to send delegates to attend.
并要求各个小组都派出代表参加
We have eight party branches since before
我们自前有八个党的小组
except that the European branch who can't come because of the long distance.
除欧洲组因路途遥远不能前来
The remaining seven branches
其余七个小组
whave all confirmed their delegates.
都已经确定了参会人选
We sent the travelling expenses to the delegates.
我们给参会代表寄去了路费
One hundred silver dollars per person.
每人一百银圆
Can Comrade Chen Duxiu and Comrade Ji Dazhao come?
陈独秀同志和季大钊同志都能来吗
Comrade Chen Duxiu,
陈独秀志呢
because of the urgent need to raise funds for universities,
因为急于筹措大学经费问题
can't attend the meeting.
不能到会
Comrade Li Dazhao,
李大钊同志呢
who is also busy hosting eight universities in Beijing,
也忙于主持北京八所大学的
dealing with the problem of teachers' salary,
教师索薪问题
can't come to Shanghai.
不能前来上海了
Southuern Chen and Northern Li are not present at the meeting.
南陈北李都不到会
Will this still make sense?
这个会还有意义吗
Chen Duxiu and Hui Xingran can't attend the meeting.
陈独秀同惠星然不能到会
But he was in charge
但整个会议的筹备领导工作
of the entire preparatory leadership of the conference.
都是他来主持的
He wrote to all the delegates
他给各个代表都写了信
and presented four points
并向大会提出了
on organization and policy to the general assembly.
关于组织和政策的四点意见
Bao Huiseng will represent Comrade Chen Duxiu
包惠僧呢将作为陈独秀同志的代表
as he attends this conference.
参加这次大会
I want to know,
我想知道
who are the comrades attending this congress?
都有哪些同志参加这次代表大会
The Shanghai branch has Li Hanjun and Li Da.
上海组有李汉俊李达
The Beijing branch has Zhang Guoshou and Liu Renjing.
北京组有张国寿 刘仁静
The Changsha branch has Mao Zedong and He Shuheng.
长沙组有毛泽东 何叔衡
The Wuhan branch has Dong Biwu and Chen Tanqiu.
武汉组有董必武 陈潭秋
The Jinan branch has Deng Enming and Wang Jinmei.
济南组有王尽美 邓恩铭
The Guangzhou branch has Chen Gongbo.
广州组有陈公博
There is also Zhou Fohai in the Japan branch
旅日组有周佛海
and Bao Huiseng.
还有包惠僧
There are thirteen members of the Communist Party of China.
总共十三位中共党员
At present, they have already started one after another.
目前都已经陆续启程了
Have they all arranged accomodation?
他们来的住处都安排好了吗
Well, we have already arranged this.
这个呢我们已经安排好了
We rented the Beaumont Girls' School
我们以北京大学
in the French Concession
暑期旅游团的名义
in the name of the Peking University summer tour group
租下了法租界的博文女校
for one month
租期一个月
and we can move in anytime.
随时可以进住
Comrade Li Da
李达同志
is now preparing for the delegates to check in.
现在正在为代表们入住做准备呢
Is the meeting also in this place?
开会也在这个地方吗
The meeting place should be absolutely safe.
开会的地方要绝对保证安全
Where exactly to open?
究竞在哪里开
We are still working on it.
我们还在研究
But there are alternatives.
不过 已经有备选方案了
So everything is ready?
这么说已经万事俱备
There's just one last thing.
只欠东风了
At the beginning of June 1921,
一九二一年六月初
Communist International representative Marin
共产国际代表马林
and foreign representative of the Communist International Far East Secretary
和共产国际远东书记外代表
Nickelski arrived in Shanghai one after another.
尼克尔斯基先后到达上海
After several conversations with Li Da and Li Hanjun,
在与李达 李汉俊几次交谈后
they suggested to convene a national congress as soon as possible
建议尽快召开全国代表大会
and formally establish the Communist Party of China.
正式成立中国共产党
Li Da and Li Hanjun,
李达李汉俊
by writing letters
通过写陈独秀和李大钊
to Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao,
书信商议
to hold the first national congress
决定在上海开中国共产党
of the Communist Party of China in Shanghai.
第一次全国代表大会
[Shanghai Bowen Girls' School]
洁畲兄
I'm so sorry.
实在抱
I couldn't pick you up at the dock yesterday.
昨天没能去码头接你
I know that you are busy.
知道你忙
What you are doing now is a great thing
你现在做的可是一件
that will open up the world.
开天辟地
Yes.
对
Good, this word is well used.
好这个词用得到位
In the end, you're a great scholar.
到底是秀才出身
You hit the nail on the head.
一语中的
Jieshe.
洁畲兄
But this epoch-making event is not easy to do.
可这开天辟地的大事不好办哪
These days, I'm in a mess.
这些天把我弄得焦头烂额
It's a mess!
狼不堪哪
Otherwise, I will pick you up at the dock.
狼损不哪
Now everyone says
现在大家都说
that you, Li Hanjun, are the second brother of our party
你李汉俊是我党的二师兄
This statement deserves its name.
这个说法实至名归呀
Brother has no time to show up.
大师兄没时间露面
I have to be reluctant.
我就只好勉为其难了
Jieshe.
洁畲兄
You must help me more!
你可一定要多帮衬我呀
If this is not done well
这件事要是没办好
then we'll all be sinners.
那我们可都成千古罪人了
Communists are always at the call of the party.
共产党人随时听候党的召唤
If you have any tasks, you can arrange them.
你有什么任务你就布置
Here.
来
This conference
这次大会
discusses the main party program
主要讨论党纲
and future practical work plan.
和今后实际工作计划
Everybody will discuss.
大家商量
Please ask you and Zhang Guotao and I,
请您和张国焘还有我
the three of us, to draft these two documents
我们三个人根据讨论意见
according to the discussion.
来起草这两个文件
Jieshe.
洁畲兄
You are a scholar of the former Qing Dynasty
你可是前清的秀才
of outstanding talent.
功力了得
This matter must belong to you.
这件事可非你莫属啊
No problem. You ask for it.
没问题 你提要求
I'll make preparations now.
我现在就做准备
Good.
好
Then I'll prepare the materials for you.
那我去给你准备材料
This is the office of Bowen Girls' School
这里呢 是博文女校的办公室
If you think it's noisy here,
你要是嫌这里吵的话
you can move to my house to write.
也可以搬去我家写
It's nice here.
这儿挺好的
What questions can you discuss with your comrades?
有什么问题还可以和同志们讨论
Will the conference be held here?
大会在这儿开吗
For security,
为了安全起见
it's better to hold the conference in my house.
大会还是在我家召开比较合适
Good.
好
Let's do it!
咱们说千就千
Seize all the time you can.
抓紧一切时间
Right. Right.
好好
Come in.
请进
Excuse me, is this Mr. Dong Biwu?
请是董必武先生吗
Yes, I'm Dong Biwu.
对 我是董必武
You are?
你是
Hello, sir.
先生 您好
I'm Mao Zedong from Hunan.
我是湖南的毛泽东
Mao Zedong of Xinmin Society.
新民学会的毛泽东
Yes.
是
Runzhi, come in, come in.
润之 来来来
Please hold this for me first.
你先帮我拿一下这个
Okay.
好
When I was walking today,
今天散步的时候啊
I scraped some peach gum.
刮了点桃胶
Just in time.
正好用上
I've heard of frugality, sir.
早就听说过先生节俭
I'm witnessing it today.
今天我算是看着了
I'm accustomed to frugality.
节俭惯了
This brush will still work.
这粘一粘还能用
Runzhi, I have long wanted to see you.
润之 早就想见你了
Please sit down.
快请坐
Please, sir.
先生请
Sir.
先生
You are a senior.
您是前辈
Please give me more advice.
还要请您多多赐教
Now, I just have a problem.
我现在啊 还正好有个问题
I want to ask you for advice.
想向你请教一下
I know you sir are drafting
我知道先生正在起草
the Party program and work plan.
党纲和工作计划
Is there anything I can do?
有什么我能做的事情
You can look forward to it.
您尽管盼吋
Marx said
马克思说
the Communist Party is the vanguard of the working class.
共产党是工人阶级的先锋队
You said if the Communist Party of China
你说我们中国共产党
fits this nature?
符合这个性质吗
I discussed it with some comrades.
我跟几个同志探讨过
We didn't arrive to a conclusion.
莫衷一是
Sir.
先生
You ask me such a question.
您问我这样的问题
I must have learned something.
想必已经有心得了
We did investigate and study
这个问题
this question.
我们确实是调查研究过
The founding of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党的成立
was never the result of a dozen or so of us,
绝不是我们这十几个
or more than fifty members of the Party nationwide,
或者是全国五十多个党员
stuck in our books and thinking about it.
关在书斋里苦思冥想的行动
It is also a product
它同样是马克思主义
of the combination of Marxism and the Chinese labor movement.
与中国劳工运动相结合的产物
For example, in Wuhan,
比如在我们武汉
there were more than 300,000 workers
就有三十多万工人
and last year we investigated
去年我们调查过
the "Hankou Labor Conditions"
在《新青年》 刊登的
published in "New Youth".
《汉口苦力状况》
This is the reality.
讲的就是这种情况
Yes.
是
I have read this investigation report.
这个调查报告我看过
Very persuasive.
很有说服力
I saw it with my own eyes.
我亲眼所见
Hunger quickly multiplies into death.
饿冻相乘 死亡甚速
No clothes in winter or summer.
衣无冬夏
Only a broken sack
仅破麻袋一片
covering the lower body.
遮其下体
This is the present situation of the porters at the Yangtze River wharf.
这就是长江码头搬运工人的现状
They move around every day,
他们每天搬来搬去
working overtime every day,
每天超负荷地工作
creating high value.
创造了很高的价值
But they themselves are living a miserable life.
可他们自己却过着牛马不如的日子
Is this their destiny?
难道这就是他们的宿命吗
No, absolutely not.
不是 绝对不是
So they are especially equipped with
所以他们特别具备
revolutionary spirit of resistance.
革命的反抗精神
We have only been in Wuhan for three years.
我们武汉仅仅这三年
There have been dozens of general strikes.
就发生了几十起大罢工
This fully shows
这充分显示了
the strength and advancement of the Chinese working class.
中国工人阶级的力量和先进性
yes.
是啊
The same is true in Changsha.
在我们长沙也是一样
The working class
工人阶级
are always at the forefront of the struggle.
始终都冲在斗争的第一线
So I said to
所以我就说
the Party branch in Wuhan,
武汉的党小组
it's definitely not the creation of a few of our scholars.
绝对不是我们几个秀才的创造
Fundamentally speaking,
从根本上讲
Wuhan now has the class base and social conditions
武汉现在已经具备了
for the establishment of an advanced working class organization
成立以马克思主义为指导思想的
with Marxism
先进工人阶级组织的阶级基础
as its guiding ideology.
和社会条件
Sir.
先生
I totally agree with you.
我完全赞同你的观点
The founding of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党的成立
is more than just
绝不仅仅是
the awakening of a handful of our intellectuals.
我们几个知识分子的觉醒
It is first and foremost the awakening of the Chinese working class.
他首先是中国 工人阶级的觉醒
It is the awakening of all Chinese people.
是全体中国人民的觉醒
Is the great awakening of the Chinese nation.
是中华民族伟大的觉醒
The Communist Party of China represents
中国共产党代表的是
the fundamental interests of the overwhelming majority of the people.
最广大人民群众的根本利益
This is our party's
这才是我们这个党
rationality and science of its founding.
今天成立的合理性和科学性
Moreso, it is the Communist Party of China's
更是中国共产党
fundamental driving force behind its vitality.
生机勃勃一往无前的根本动力
Great.
太好了
This problem is solved.
这个问题就解决了
Runzhi.
润之
You and I can talk all night.
你我二人 彻夜长谈
Good.
好
[Guangzhou]
先生 我被挑选为去莫斯科学习
I have come to report to you on the work of the Socialist Youth League.
特意来向您汇报社会主义青年团的工作
which will soon hold a conference with the first national congress
马上就要召开中国共产党
of the Communist Party of China.
第一次全国代表大会了
We hope to be able to express our appreciation for the league's work
我们希望能够对团的工作
and give clearer instructions.
做出更加明确的指示
This time in order to make
这次为了能使
the first Communist Party of China conference hold successfully,
中国共产党一大顺利召开
I and Comrade Li Dazhao from Beijing
我和北京的李大钊同志
have done a lot of preparatory work,
都做了很多准备工作
including how to strengthen the work of the Socialist Youth League.
包括如何加强社会主义青年团的工作
We all responded.
我们也都做了回复
Bao Huiseng, as my designated representative,
包惠僧作为我指定的代表
have already set off with Chen Gongbo.
已经跟陈公博一起出发了
This time I believe
这次我相信
the first national congress of the Communist Party of China
一大作为中国共产党
will be a sign of formal establishment.
正式成立的标志
It will be a great success.
一定会开得很成功
Unfortunately,
可惜的是
I'm also the pre-university principal here,
我在这儿兼着大学预科校长
I need to raise money.
需要筹款
I really can't get away.
实在是脱不开身
Comrade Li Dazhao
李大钊同志
also can't attend the meeting because of Peking University affairs.
也因北大事务缠身不能到会
This is a great pity.
这是很大的遗撼
However, sir, I'm sorry that you can't attend the meeting.
先生 然您不能到会有些遗撼
But the Communist Party of China will be born.
但中国共产党的横空出世
It will be an epoch-making event.
必将是个划时代的大事件
I believe it.
我相信
Zhongxie.
仲
Aren't you going to attend the preparations?
你不是要去参加筹备
Is it the job of China Labor Union Secretariat?
中国劳动组合书记部的工作吗
How did you get to Guangdong?
怎么也到广东了
I'm from Shanghai, Mr. Zhongfu.
我从上海过来 仲甫先生
I brought you two things.
我给您带来两个东西
What is it?
什么呀
This is what Mr. Yi Baisha asked me to deliver to you
这是上个月易自沙先生到上海
when he arrived in Shanghai last month.
属托我转交给您的
Two days ago Mr. Yi Baisha went to Beijing alone
前两天易自沙先生只身前往北京
to assassinate Xu Shichang unsuccessfully.
刺杀徐世昌未果
He jumped into the sea angrily,
愤然跳海
committing suicide.
自杀了
What about the second thing?
第二件事情呢
This is just sent by Shiyan from France.
这是世炎刚从法国寄过来的
Lyrics of the "Internationale".
《国际歌》 的歌词
Do you know the lyrics of these last chorus?
您知道这最后几句副歌的歌词
Who translated it?
是谁翻译的吗
Who!,
谁
Qiaonian.
乔年
Chen Qiaonian.
陈乔年
Shiyan specifically mentioned in the letter,
世炎在信上特别提到
he said Yannian and Qiaonian were going through
说延年和乔年正在经历着一场
a great fracture in life.
人生的伟大的裂变
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
The three of you are finally going to be
你们父子三人终于要成为
a comrade-in-arms in the same trench.
同一个战壕的战友了
I'm really happy for you guys.
我真为你们感到高兴
Rise up, hungry and cold slaves.
起来 饥寒交迫的奴隶们
Rise up, all the world's suffering people.
起来 全世界受苦的人
The blood is boiling,
满腔的热血已经沸腾
fighting for the truth.
要为真理而斗争
[Kangmuyizhai, Beijing]
同志们
Today is the Beijing branch of the Communist Party of China's
今天是中国共产党北京支部
and the Marxist Theory Research Society's
和马克思学说研究会
joint situation report meeting,
共同举办的形势报告会
an the workers' club in Changxindian
而且长辛店的工人俱乐部
have also sent representatives to attend.
也派出代表前来参加
Let's give a big round of applause.
让我们以热烈的掌声
Please welcome their arrival.
欢迎他们的到来
Next,
接下来
we welcome Comrade Ge Shugui.
我们有请葛树贵同志
Let's introduce Changxindian to us
来为我们介绍一下长辛店
and the national workers' movement.
和全国工人运动的情况
Welcome.
大家欢迎
Mr. Shouchang, let me say something
守常先生让我说两句
Then I will say a few words to you all.
那我就跟大家伙说两句
First of all, I want to tell you good news.
首先呢要告诉大家一个好消息
On 1 May of this year,
今年的五月一层
we railway workers in Changxindian
我们长辛店铁路工人
held a grand celebration meeting.
举行了隆重的庆祝大会
The Changxindian Railway Workers Union is formally established.
正式成立了长辛店铁路工人工会
This is, under the leadership of the Communist Party,
这是共产党领导下的
a party branch of railway workers.
铁路工人的组织
It is an important revolutionary body
是党发动和领导工人运动的
for the Party to mobilize and lead the workers' movement.
重要的革命体
Now we not only have railway unions,
我们现在不仅有了铁路工会
but we also have the machinists union,
我们还有机器工会
printers union,
印刷工会
rickshaw pullers union, etc.
人力车夫工会等
With all kinds of industrial trade unions and handicraft trade unions
各类产业工会和手工业工会
under the organization and leadership of various trade unions,
在各类工会的组织和领导下
the workers' movements in major cities across the country continue to rise.
全国各大城市的工人运动持续高涨
The consciousness of the working class is constantly improving.
工人阶级的觉悟不断地提高
Now, a number of leading individuals
现在已经涌现出了一批
with communist ideals have emerged.
具有共产主义思想的先进分子
What does this mean?
这说明什么
This shows that in the Chinese political arena,
这说明了在中国的政治舞台上
we the working class
我们工人阶级
will play an increasingly important role.
正在发挥越来越大的重要作用
We have become the main force of the revolution.
我们已经成为了革命的主力军
Comrades,
同志们
I also want to report good news to you.
我也要给大家报告一个喜讯
the First National Congress of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党第一次全国代表大会
is being held in the south.
正在南方举行
The Communist Party of China is formally established!
中国共产党正式成立了
Hurrah!
好 好 好
This is an epoch-making event!
这是开天辟地的一件大事
Comrades,
同志们
the establishment of the Communist Party of China was not accidental.
中国共产党的成立他不是偶然的
Since the Opium War,
他是自鸦片战争以来
it is the inevitable outcome of China's historical development.
中国历史发展的必然产物
It is our Chinese people's
他是我们中国人民
inevitable product of tenacious exploration
在救亡图荐的斗争中
in the struggle to save the nation from subjugation.
顽强探索的必然产物
It is our Chinese nation's
他是我们门中华民族
inevitable product of constant awakening
在追求振兴的道路上
on the road of pursuing rejuvenation.
不断觉醒的必然产物
Comrades,
同志们
the birth of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党的诞生
means that the Chinese Revolution
意味着我们中国革命
will now have a strong leadership core.
从此以后有了坚强的领导核心
This will lay a solid foundation for the inevitable success
这为我们事业今后必然成功
for our cause in the future.
打下了坚实的基础
Comrades,
同志们
the last line of the "Internationale":
《国际歌》的最后一句歌词
"The Internationale shall be realised!"
英特纳雄耐尔就一定要实现
This is the highest goal
这是我们共产党人
that we communists pursue
共同追求的最高目标
and also the highest stage of human social development.
也是人类社会发展的最高阶段
Comrades, three years ago,
同志们三年前
I gave a speech in Central Park.
我在中央公园有过一次演讲
There was a sentence in it.
里边有一句话
The future world
试看将来的环球
will be a world of red flags.
必是赤旗的世界
So today,
那么今天
I also solemnly tell you
我也郑重地跟大家
my latest insight.
说一说我最新的心得
That is,
那就是
only by taking the socialist road
中国只有走社会主义道路
can China realize
他才能够实现
the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.
中华民族之振兴
And I firmly believe,
而且我坚信
one hundred years from now,
一百年以后的中国
China will prove my point today.
他必会证明我今天的观点
Socialism will never fail China!
社会主义绝不会辜负中国
[Li Dazhao, pioneer of the Chinese communist movement, great Marxist, outstanding proletarian revolutionary, co-founder of the Communist Party of China. Killed in 1927 by a reactionary warlord in Beijing, at age 38]
[李大钊，中国共产主义运动的先驱，伟大的马克思主义者，杰出的无产阶级革命家，中国共产党的主要创始人之一。1927年被反动军阀杀害于北京，时年38岁。]
[Site of the First National Congress of the Communist Party of China]
[中国共产党第一次全国代表大会会址]
"Such simple beginnings
其作始也简
brought a momumental future."
其将毕也必巨
Against the backdrop of the unprecedented crisis
在中华民族内忧外患
of domestic turmoil and foreign threats facing the Chinese nation,
社会危机空前深重的背景下
in combining Marxism-Leninism
在马克思列宁主义
with the Chinese workers' movement,
同中国工人运动相结合的进程中
the Communist Party of China was born.
中国共产党诞生了
China gave rise to the Communist Party.
中国产生了共产党
This is an epoch-making event.
这是开天辟地的大事变
This epoch-making event
这一开天辟地的大事变
has profoundly changed, since modern times,
深刻改变了近代以后
the direction and course of the development of the Chinese nation.
中华民族发展的方向和进程
It has profoundly changed the Chinese people's
深刻改变了中国人民
and the Chinese nation's future and destiny.
和中华民族的前途和命运
It has profoundly changed
深刻改变了
the trends and patterns of world development.
世界发展的趋势和格局
The birth of the Communist Party of China
中国共产党的诞生
is the inevitable result of the historical choice of modern China.
是近代中国历史选择的必然结果
It is the inevitable result of the choice of the Chinese people.
是中国人民选择的必然结果
Since the Communist Party of China came into being,
自从有了中国共产党
the disaster-striken Chinese people,
灾难深重的中国人民
with reliable organizations and leaders,
有了可以信赖的组织和领导者
began their great journey to achieve national independence,
开始了实现民族独立
people's liberation,
人民解放
national prosperity,
和国家富强
and happiness for the people.
人民幸福的伟大征程
[The End]
[全剧终]